Guide to the Gilbert Theodore Rowe Papers, 1878-1965
Duke University. University Archives
Gilbert Theodore Rowe papers 1878-1965
Duke University. University Archives
Rowe, Gilbert Theodore
1 linear foot Extent: 750 Items
Gilbert Theodore Rowe was born in Salisbury, NC on September 10, 1875. His father was Joseph Columbus Rowe, a Methodist minister. He received his A.B. and D.D. from Trinity College in 1895 and 1914, respectively. He earned his S.T.D. at Temple University in 1905 and was awarded a Litt.D. from Duke University in 1925. In 1928, he returned to Duke University as Professor and Chair of Christian Doctrine and remained until his retirement in 1949. The collection includes correspondence, clippings and Dr. Rowe's sermon notes, as well as material pertaining to his father, Joseph Columbus Rowe. The collection ranges in date from 1878-1965
RL.01827
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Gilbert Theodore Rowe Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1970, 1977.
Biographical Note
Gilbert Theodore Rowe was born in Salisbury, NC on September 10, 1875. His father was Joseph Columbus Rowe, a Methodist minister. He received his A.B. and D.D. from Trinity College in 1895 and 1914, respectively. He earned his S.T.D. at Temple University in 1905 and was awarded a Litt.D. from Duke University in 1925. He was admitted to the Western North Carolina Conference in 1896, only six years after the two state conferences were formed. Received into Full Connection in 1898, he began to serve pastorates, in eleven successive appointments, until 1920. It was while he served the church at Albemarle that he married Caroline Pearle Bostian in 1902. They had two sons.
In 1920, Dr. Rowe became editor, first of the North Carolina Christian Advocate and then of the Methodist Quarterly Review at Nashville until 1928, serving simultaneously as Book Editor for the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. It was in this period that he produced his works, The Meaning of Methodism and Reality in Religion for the 1927 Quillian Lectures at Emory University.
In 1928, Dr. Rowe accepted an offer from Duke President William Few to return to his alma mater as Professor and Chair of Christian Doctrine in the School of Religion at Duke University. He served as Professor of Christine Doctrine at the University until his retirement in 1949, and continued to serve both Duke and the Methodist church until his death on February 10, 1960.
Collection Overview
Materials include Dr. Rowe's sermon notes, correspondence, and clippings. His sermon notes are largely handwritten and often appear on the back of other material, such as correspondence, letterhead, envelopes, church bulletins, and programs. The collection also includes some material concerning Dr. Rowe's father, Joseph Columbus Rowe (1848-1920). The collection ranges in dates from 1878-1965.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. School of Religion; Duke University. Divinity School; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Alumni and alumnae; Rowe, Gilbert Theodore, 1875-1960; Methodism -- North Carolina; Sermons, American -- 20th century
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Junaluska School of Religion Records, 1928-1941
Duke University Archives
United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Sermon Notes and Bulletins, 1897-1932, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermon Notes, 1899-1918, undated
  - Sermon Notes and Bulletins, 1916-1954, undated
  - Sermon Notes, 1910-1955, undated
  - Sermon Notes, 1907-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1965, undated
  - Correspondence regarding Dr. Rowe's coming to Duke University to teach, 1927-1928
  - Notes on Methodism, circa 1930s
  - Clippings
  - Miscellaneous
  - Joseph Columbus Rowe, Subscriber's Book, The People's Common Sense Medical Advisor, 1878-1884
  - Joseph Columbus Rowe, composition books, 1917 June 13, undated
  - Trinity Archive, 1895
  - Photographs